<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Climate | Nkeiru C.</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tag/climate/</link><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/climate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Climate</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:01:26 -0400</lastBuildDate><image><url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_a0dc1595079f9789.png</url><title>Climate</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tag/climate/</link></image><item><title>What if your local government used the earth to heat and cool homes?.</title><link>http://localhost:1313/blog/municipal-tens/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:01:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/municipal-tens/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thermal Energy Networks: The Municipal Perspective
My work as a Clean Energy Intern at the City of Albany, Office of Sustainability&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With new regulations, an influx in climate funds, and gas and water infrastructure reaching end of life,
municipalities especially in New York State have a lot of potential to be apart of the thermal energy network/district
energy space but it requires partnering with the private sector, the non profit sector and most importantly, the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is (among many others) the conclusion I came to after researching the question of the role of municipalities in
the development and operation of thermal energy networks in their communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This report discusses:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>-equity concerns and TENs role in climate justice&lt;br>
-the TEN regulation landscape in New York State&lt;br>
-potential ownership models&lt;br>
-TENS and their possible relationship with municipal water &amp;amp; sewer departments&lt;br>
-a municipalty&amp;rsquo;s possible role in utility company owned TEN (or UTEN)&lt;br>
-my recommendations for municipalities especially in NYS&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crowning achievement of my time as a
at the
is this report Thermal Energy Networks: A Municipal Perspective. I wrote it in response to actual questions asked of me by my bosses at the City of Albany and also answered some of my own questions. The audience is any municipal official with report sections relevant to the Public Works official, Sustainability Officer and more. I invite you to read it below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>